A Guide to the Joan Girone papers, 1970-2012
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Joan Girone papers, 1970-2012
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 284
9.9 linear feet.
Girone, Joan, 1929-2019
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Joan Girone in 1990 with additional accrual in 2012.
Biographical / Historical Information
Joan Girone was a Chesterfield County politician and the first woman to serve on the Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors. She was born August 30, 1929, in Toronto, Ontario, Canada. Girone worked as a children's wear buyer in New York City before moving to Chesterfield in 1965. She actively participated in the local community by serving on the Chesterfield PTA board and writing the Bon Air community newsletter. Along with fellow Republicans, she fought against the consolidation of the Chesterfield, Henrico, and Richmond City school systems ordered by Judge Robert R. Merhige in 1972 which aimed to integrate the public schools. She assisted in the founding of both the Friends of Chesterfield County Public Library and the Capital Area Agency on Aging in 1973. In 1976, Girone ran for office and was elected to the Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors. She went on to be reelected in 1979 and 1983.
As a moderate conservative Republican, Girone opposed active government involvement. She advocated for issues such as the banning of leaf burning in Chesterfield county, the extension of Powhite Parkway, and opposition of the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT II) program by the federal government. Additionally, she regularly participated in drafting the annual Bon Air Community Plans which laid out future community projects and goals.
Girone made bids for the Republican candidacy for Virginia State Senate in 1980 and 1987. She was unable to secure convention delegate support in both primaries, but ran as an independent candidate in the 1987 election against incumbent Republican Senator Robert Russell. She did not succeed in the senate race. Despite her losses, she continued to serve the Chesterfield community after the end of her final supervisor term in 1987.
Her service to Chesterfield continued through participation in government committees and community groups such as the Midlothian YMCA and the Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan Steering Committee. She worked as a real estate salesperson in Chesterfield County until her death. She died April 14, 2019 in Richmond, VA.
Sources: Richmond Times-Dispatch, "Joan Girone, first woman elected to Chesterfield Board of Supervisors, dies at 91," (https://www.richmond.com/news/obituary/joan-girone-first-woman-elected-to-chesterfield-board-of-supervisors/article_25d7b234-9794-5635-adf7-06731aaa3cac.html)
Scope and Contents
The Joan Girone papers, 1970-2012, is a collection of materials used by Chesterfield County, VA politician Joan Girone. The papers provide insight into the administrative duties of local government in the Richmond area during the 1970s and 1980s. The collection also includes senate and supervisor campaign files which deliver a unique look into the logistical and political mechanisms for running a local or state campaign. Additionally, the general Republican campaign files highlight the platforms and grassroots movements implemented by the Virginia Republican Party in the 1970s and 1980s.
Series 1: Public Service Administrative Files, 1970-2011: The bulk of the collection is comprised of documents related to Joan Girone's service to the Chesterfield community both as a private citizen and elected official. These documents include professional correspondence with constituents, drafts of Bon Air Community Plans, constituent surveys, personal planners, and documents pertaining to specific issues Girone advocated for or against.
The correspondence is composed of general letters written by constituents or colleagues regarding assorted issues in the Chesterfield community such as infrastructure repair, policy recommendations, professional congratulations, and general concerns related to Chesterfield and the greater Richmond area. Responses from Girone are attached to some letters.
The personal notepads and desk planners include Girone's schedules and notes from her time serving as supervisor. The notepads contain notes from meetings and lists for daily plans; these include Bon Air community meetings, campaign tasks, and reminders to respond to correspondence. The desk planners contain calendars of specific events and meetings which Girone participated in as supervisor.
Included in this series are materials pertaining to issues and groups in the Chesterfield community such as Abandoned Coal Mine Land Program, the YMCA of Greater Richmond, Republican Women's Club, Chesterfield road restoration, and the SALT II international treaty. The files contain correspondence and notes by Girone regarding the issues and her related stance.
Also within the series is a collection of buttons owned by Girone. The buttons were worn by Girone to promote numerous viewpoints. Content of the buttons include the Stop ERA movement, the promotion of the Powhite Parkway Extension Program, participation in the VCU Center for Women's Health, and Friends of Chesterfield Library. Additionally, the collection includes campaign buttons for Republican candidates such as Eva Scott, John Warner, John Dalton, and Richard Obenshain.
Series 2: Campaign Files, 1971-1987: The collection also includes material used by Girone for her own and others' campaigns for public office. The files contain material from Girone's supervisor campaigns, state senate campaigns, and general Republican campaigns of other local, state, and national nominees.
The supervisor campaign files are comprised of materials used by Girone for her 1976, 1979, and 1983 campaigns for Chesterfield supervisor. The files include correspondence with voters, supporters, and constituents, questionnaires to voters, candidacy petitions, promotional material, and expenditure reports.
The state senate campaign files consist of fundraising reports, recorded endorsements, debate recordings, promotional material, mailings, surveys, platform statements, news releases, and correspondence. The files cover both attempts by Girone to obtain the Republican nomination for state senate, as well as her campaign as an independent candidate. In addition to material primarily used to promote and support her campaigns, there are research files concerning her major opponents, Tom Bliley in 1980 and Robert Russell in 1987.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series 1: Public Service Administrative Files, 1970-2012 and Series 2: Campaign Files, 1971-1987.
Girone, Joan, 1929-2019
- Series 1: Public Service Administrative Files, 1970-2012
  - Abandoned Coal Mine Land Program, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Bon Air Green Company, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Draft Plan, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Draft Plan, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Draft Plan, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Finalized Plan, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Land Use Planning, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Meeting Notes, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bon Air Community Plan - Memoranda and Statements, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bon Air Community Newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bon Air Community Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Certificates and Honors, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Certificates and Honors - Gavel, 1984 (Item Gavel)
  - Certificates and Honors - Oversize, 1978-1988 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Certificates and Honors - Plaques, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Correspondence, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Draft, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Proposal, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Land Use Map, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Briefings (folder 1), 2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Briefings (folder 2), 2009 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Briefings (folder 3), 2009 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Briefings (folder 1), 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Briefings (folder 2), 2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Issue Policies, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Steering Committee Notes, 2009-2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chesterfield Comprehensive Plan - Zoning Maps, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chesterfield Population Loss, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chesterfield Police Department - Correspondence and Reports, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chesterfield Police Department - Correspondence and Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chesterfield Police Department - Newsletter, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chesterfield Religious Community Outreach, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chesterfield Republican Committee Propositions, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Constituent Rolodex Cards - A-D, undated (Box 16)
  - Constituent Rolodex Cards - E-K, undated (Box 17)
  - Constituent Rolodex Cards - L-R, undated (Box 18)
  - Constituent Rolodex Cards - S-Z, undated (Box 19)
  - Constituent Survey, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - General, 1970-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - General, 1982-1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - General, 1987-2009 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Daily Desk Planner, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Friends of Chesterfield Library, 1978-1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Henrico GOP Convention Membership, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Canvassing Material, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Correspondence, 1977-1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - County Solid Waste Study, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - County Ordinance, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Petitions, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Leaf Burning Ban - Statements and Reports, 1980-1986 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1971-1985 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Passenger Rail Investment and Improvement Act, 2008-2012 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 1), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 2), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 3), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 4), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Personal Notepad, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 1), 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 2), 1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Personal Notepad, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Personal Notepad, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Personal Notepad, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Personal Notepad, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Personal Notepad, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Personal Notepad, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Personal Notepad, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 1), 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 2), 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 1), 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Personal Notepad (folder 2), 1986 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Pluggers" Cartoon, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Political Button Collection, 1973-1996 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1970-2009 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Powhite Parkway Extension - Correspondence, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Powhite Parkway Extension - Facility Operations Review, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Republican Women's Club, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Resumes and Biographical Sketches, 1975-1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Richmond First Club, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Road Restoration Fund Disputes, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - SALT II Opposition, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - School Consolidation - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - School Consolidation - Parents Against Busing, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - School Consolidation - Reports and Releases, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1971-1995 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Student Projects, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Virginia County Supervisors' Manual, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Virginia PTA Congress, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Women's Health Advisory Council, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - YMCA of Greater Richmond - Memory Book, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - YMCA of Greater Richmond - Midlothian Campaign, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Campaign Files, 1971-1987
  - Campaign Ephemera, 1979-1987 (Box 21)
  - Republican Campaigns - Coleman, Marshall, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Republican Campaigns - Dalton, John, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Republican Campaigns - General Mailings, 1975-1984 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Republican Campaigns - Durrette, Wyatt, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Republican Campaigns - Miller, Nathan H., 1978 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Republican Campaigns - Obenshain, Richard D., 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Republican Campaigns - Scott, Eva, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Republican Campaigns - Warner, John, 1978-1984 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Senate Campaigns - Bliley, Tom, Campaign Research, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Senate Campaigns - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Senate Campaigns - Debate Recordings, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Senate Campaigns - Election Results, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Senate Campaigns - Friends of Joan Girone Campaign Headquarters Lease, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Senate Campaign - Endorsement Ad Recording, 1987 (Box 20)
  - Senate Campaigns - Fundraising Guides, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Senate Campaigns - Financial Contribution Reports, 1980-1988 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Senate Campaign - Fundraiser Guest Book (folder 1), 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Senate Campaign - Fundraiser Guest Book (folder 2), 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Senate Campaign - George Jones Endorsement Recording, 1987 (Box 20)
  - Senate Campaign - Mailings, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Senate Campaign - Platform Statements and News Releases, 1979-1987 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Senate Campaign - Promotional Material, 1980-1987 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Senate Campaign - Republican Delegate Certification, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Senate Campaign - Richmond Republican Prefiling, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Senate Campaign - Russell, Robert E. Campaign Research, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Senate Campaign - Survey Results, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Senate Campaign - Television Interview Recording, undated (Box 20)
  - Senate Campaigns - Third Congressional District of Virginia Benchmark Survey (folder 1), 1980 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Senate Campaigns - Third Congressional District of Virginia Benchmark Survey (folder 2), 1980 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Candidacy Petition, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Constituent Questionnaire Results (folder 1), 1983 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Constituent Questionnaire Results (folder 2), 1983 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Constituent Questionnaire Results (folder 3), 1983 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Contributions and Expenditures, 1975-1983 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Oath of Office, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Supervisor Campaign - Publicity Material, 1979-1983 (Box 15, Folder 5)